finally the wave is over iOS version
16.4 was just released with support for
an API that web developers have been
waiting for a long time since long long
ago Google has been pushing the idea of
pwx progressive web applications pwas
are websites that look feel and act just
like apps they can be saved on the home
screen and next to real apps they have a
splash screen they have offline support
they can do almost what a native app can
do pwas are possible because browsers
are getting more and more powerful
thanks on a big part to Google enabling
the newest apis on Google Chrome but in
a world where websites can be as
powerful and can do almost as much as
native apps companies like apple my
field threatened since the App Store is
a billion dollar business this is why
Apple has been notoriously low on
implementing support for pwas on iOS
specifically they have taken an
extremely long time enabling support for
a feature that can make or break a pwa a
feature that has been in Chrome since
2015. that feature is web push
notifications until now if you wanted to
send push notifications to the iPhone of
your users the only option you had was
to make an IOS app there was no way
around it but since iOS 16.4 you can
send notifications to the iPhone of your
users directly from your own website it
is now finally possible to reach users
on iPhone Android Chrome Firefox Edge
Opera and Safari with one piece of code
a marketer's degree so let's see how
this API works and how you can Implement
web push notifications on your own
website first on our server we will
generate a public and a private with key
these keys will be used to sign our
notifications we use signatures to
authenticate our server with the
notification servers of Apple Google and
the rest we don't have to generate those
keys manually instead we can use a
package in our case we're going to use
the node.js web push package but you can
also find web push packages for rust PHP
Java c-sharp Python and others on our
server all we have to do is import the
web push package and call the function
and generate vapid Keys we then console
log the resulting keys that looks
something like this it is important we
run this code only once and store the
keys somewhere safe the front-end code
is really simple on the HTML we have a
button that says subscribe and we also
have a JavaScript import on the
JavaScript side we first have to
register a service worker a service
worker is a tiny piece of JavaScript
code that we can save on the user's disk
and that will run on the background even
after the user leave our website it is
on the service worker where we are going
to listen for push notifications and
whenever they come in we're going to
display them to register a service
worker we first have to check if the
Navigator supports it if that is true we
just call
navigator.serviceworker.register with
our service worker file that contains
this code here we are telling our
service worker to listen for push events
when a push event happens we want to get
the title of the notification by
accessing the event data and then we
call the function show notification to
actually show the push notification to
the user in our code we are only sending
the title of the notification but if we
wanted to we can send a body for more
extra content we can specify icons
actions and even vibration patterns okay
so we are ready to receive notifications
but now we actually have to start
sending them to do this first we have to
ask the user for permission and then we
have to subscribe the user to our
notifications back in our main.js file
we grab the button from our HTML and
when it is clicked we wait for our
service worker to be ready and then get
access to it then we try to get the
current post notification subscription
because maybe the user is already
subscribed if the subscription is found
we should send it to our backend to save
it on our database if the subscription
does not exist we are going to subscribe
the user to a new one the Subscribe
function takes a user visible only
required parameter that we should set to
true and it also takes an application
server key which is the public key that
we generated in our backend a while ago
after the subscription is created we
should send it to our backend and save
it on our database it's important to
save the subscription on your database
because you will need it later when you
want to send and notifications to your
users here is how a subscription looks
like after the user has been subscribed
as you can see it has an endpoint and a
couple of keys the endpoint will look
different depending on the browser that
creates the subscription in this case
this is a safari subscription so we get
web.pushed that apple on our endpoint if
it was Chrome the endpoint will start
with googleapis.com or if it was Firefox
it would start with push that services
that Mozilla if we now go to our browser
and click on the button we are going to
get asked for notification permissions
and after we accept we are going to be
subscribed now it is time to send the
notifications on our backend the code to
do that looks like this first we need
the keys that we generated on the first
step then with the web push about our
keys as you can see I also wrote my
email there we write the email in case
the Push Services need to get in touch
with the website's admin finally we call
the send notification function which
takes two arguments the first one is the
subscription that we generated in the
front end before you should load the
subscription from your database and the
second one is the data of the
notification here we can put a simple
string or some Json like this if you
decide to send a Json instead of a
string on your notification you need to
change your service worker a little bit
where instead of doing
events.txt you will do
event.data.json as you can see when we
run the code the browsers that we have
subscribed to will all show us a
notification thanks to our service
worker being active and listening done
we are now sending notifications to the
browsers of our users awesome but this
code does not work for iOS for now this
is because Apple doesn't allow just any
website to send push notifications only
bwas saved by the user can do that
thankfully turning our website into a
pwa is super easy what we are going to
do is create a manifest.json file and
we're going to link it on the head of
our website on this manifest.json we
write the name of our app we say that we
want it to be displayed without any
browser UI and we give it an icon to be
displayed on the screen of the user
after that is done on our Safari browser
we can go to our website and save it to
our home screen and as you can see our
pwa looks like any other app when we
open the app we can click on the
Subscribe button and as you can see we
will get asked for notification
permissions which we are going to accept
if we close the app lock our phone and
send the notification from our backend
we will see the notification with our
icon on our lock screen awesome and
that's it we are now sending
notifications everywhere our users are
without building a native app we are
done if you found this video useful
please consider liking it and
subscribing to the channel and let me
know in the comments what do you think
about this API and if you're going to
implement it in your website if you
haven't already and don't forget that if
you want to learn things like JavaScript
python react react native gold Dart
router among many others for absolutely
free all you have to do is click the
link below to join any of our many free
courses that you can take right now for
absolutely free with me click the link
below and I will see you there
see you on the next one bye
[Music]
thank you